<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal Elevator Pitch on 10 Pines Blog</title>
    <link>http://egutter.github.io/prueba-blog/categories/personal-elevator-pitch/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal Elevator Pitch on 10 Pines Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 15:26:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://egutter.github.io/prueba-blog/categories/personal-elevator-pitch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for introducing yourself in a conference or &#39;the conference elevator pitch&#39;</title>
      <link>http://egutter.github.io/prueba-blog/2015/10/13/the-conference-elevator-pitch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 15:26:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://egutter.github.io/prueba-blog/2015/10/13/the-conference-elevator-pitch/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It could sounds basic, but when you talk with people in a conference, you have to think quickly. So it&amp;rsquo;s very important to have in mind a successful path to a productive five-minutes chat. After being talking with a lot of people and making a lot of mistakes (since not knowing what to say about what our company do, to not asking how to contact him/her back); I’ve decided to write down a guidelines to introduce yourself and getting to know the other person, avoiding typical mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;must-ask-questions-and-its-must-remember-answers&#34;&gt;Must-ask questions (and its must-remember answers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to talk, but sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s more important and more difficult to listen. That&amp;rsquo;s why I prefer to start talking about what you need to hear and know from the person in front of you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s her/his name?&lt;/strong&gt; Basic, but sometimes when you are in a rush, you forget this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does she/he do?&lt;/strong&gt; Again, basic. But a lot of times I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself speaking a lot about what I do in order to convince the other how great we are, that I forgot to know and understand what this guy does. And this is one of the most important things in order to identify how you can make synergy together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can you contact her/him back?&lt;/strong&gt; This is important so you can continue your conversation if a potential lead emerges from the talk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it&amp;rsquo;s not important to ask the questions like this or in this order; what it is really important is that at the end of the conversation you know these 3 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you know his/her name,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what his/her company do,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and how you can contact him/her&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-i-need-to-tell-from-me&#34;&gt;What do I need to tell from me?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is really important also to let him/her know about you. And since you have a very short limited time, you have to choose very careful what do you want the other person to remember. So here it&amp;rsquo;s the top 3 messages you should always send:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is my name and the name of my company?&lt;/strong&gt; This is important so he/she can later connect your name or your company name with other things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do I/we do?&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s important to be wide open, but not to much. So try to be special in something, but let space for match with the interests of your audition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With who?&lt;/strong&gt; Here I encourage to choose your top 3 clients. Not the most important for your company but the most well known.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;template-elevator-pitch-to-introduce-myself&#34;&gt;Template elevator pitch to introduce myself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, saying this, and in order to have a training and think about this basic but important things, I create a template for sort of an elevator pitch to introduce yourself. Again, you could think this is worthless, but try doing it and you will discover that it&amp;rsquo;s not so easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% blockquote %}
My template elevator pitch to introduce myself&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My name is&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My company does&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We work with&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My name is Jorge Silva, I work at 10Pines, a south america company based in Buenos Aires&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My company does great software for great companies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Such as Starbucks, 8thLight and Teespring
{% endblockquote %}&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now is your turn, tell me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And how can I contact you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. Simple and straightforward.
Hope this is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>